Listen to a talk in an anthropology class.
Man:
Often when we think of mummies, we think of ancient Egyptians
and their elaborate methods of preserving bodies.
We used to think Egyptians were the only people practicing mummification during the Bronze
Age, about, oh, 4000 years ago,
because typical mummies are found in places, for example, with very dry climates like Egypt.
But then archaeologists discovered a site in Scotland with evidence of mummification.
And Scotland is, well, wet, rainy.
This site is called Cladh Hallan, the only place in Britain where we found
prehistoric Bronze Age mummies.
So researchers unearthed skeletons at Cladh Hallan, including a man
and a woman from around 1500 BCE.
Since these were just skeletons, the researchers didn't realize at first that they had actually been mummies.
That realization came after doing a test called radiocarbon dating on the bones.
Radiocarbon dating revealed that the man and woman had died several hundred years before being buried.
Normally, such a long wait would turn a body into a pile of bones,
not an actual skeleton like what was found.
So their bodies must have been purposely preserved for hundreds of years before burial.
Why?
Well, who knows?
But we do know how.
The bodies were preserved, mummified in a peat bog.
Peat bogs are kind of like swamps, except their conditions prevent organic materials like
bodies from fully breaking down.
They stay more intact.
Prehistoric people in Scotland used to preserve animal fat like butter in peat bogs,
so they definitely had the concept.